Moving onto the
application Layer, Chapter 2.
We will talk about how
the applications work.
And we will have three
applications, if not more.
Three are HTTP, File
transfer, email, and DNS -
Four, right there.
And we will talk about how
peer to peer applications work. So
we already talked about much of it.
I'm just going to kind of review it because
at least the protocol layers are
repeated from the previous module.
And then we talk about client-
server versus peer to peer. And some basic
concepts of names, addresses, and ports.
Now here's the issue why we have to talk
about names, addresses, and ports before
we go into applications.
This particular
book that we're following
is called top-down.
And top-down means
that it covers the
application layer first
and then it goes down.
And that is non-traditional
in the sense that you need
to know IP before you can understand
TCP, and you need to know TCP before
you can understand
applications. So this is
the first book that was
written upside down.
And to do that we need to tell you
a little bit about these lower layers
before we go into the applications. So
that is what we're doing in this module.
And the other part of this -
So for the applications
Battery was not taken out last time.
Just put the battery in, OK
then. Alright, let's go to this.
So, these are the
applications that we're
going to talk about.
They all run on TCP, UDP.
Actually, these two run on UDP,
these four run on TCP; and down.
We already know that kind of layer
diagram, right? So let's talk about how
the applications work.
There are two kinds of
applications, client-server
or peer-to-peer.
Client-server is, we talked about
it in the very first or second class,
we said that there's a server
somewhere and then
the clients all approach it.
Or request something from
it, so it's a client-requested
service. The server
provides the service
and it's just always on, always
waiting. A web server is a good example,
if you have a web server you have to leave
it on 24 hours a day, seven days a week.
Anybody can come in anytime and
request that page. Severs are always up
and clients do not
communicate directly with
each other. The clients
don't know who other
clients are and the
server is generally kept
in a data center. An
example is the best server
search engine like Google or
a social network like Facebook.
Right? If there are any questions,
please raise your hand at any time.
OK, so I'm going to keep moving -
Peer to peer works differently.
Peer to peer, all of you know -
how many of you have used
torrents? Alright. Those of you
who have not raised a hand,
please do. Not a bad thing,
because that is what you will learn in this
lecture, is that it's much more efficient.
Than doing it the way we used to do
before. And in fact, all the big companies,
including Microsoft and
other companies that
distribute their software,
use peer to peer.
So let me start with
that. OK, peer to peer
means that you gave
your file to somebody else.
Somebody gives you a file to you and so on.
So this is just between the people, between
the clients, the files are exchanged.
Understood? Peer-to-peer.
So your phone is going to
give something to this computer,
and this phone is going to give it to this
computer and this computer is going to
give it to that phone and so on so forth.
Alright? And so the hosts
communicate directly -
and so they are called peers.
And the host may come on or
off anytime. So that's the problem.
If you expected a file from somebody
and they're not there, what do you do?
Right? So file sharing with BitTorrent,
emule, Limewire, telefony, Skype,
They are all examples
of peer-to-peer, I mean
Telephony. If your mom
is not there, you call.
You know, I mean, that's a big problem,
but if you just want to call anybody,
I'm sure you will find
somebody. So that is the
situation here, is that
if you want to get a file,
somebody might have it and you might get
it at any time. And it's highly scalable,
so this one scales very well.
You could have millions of people
sharing a movie or whatever it is
they want to share, and as opposed
to on your server, it will
just get overloaded. OK.
So it is highly symmetric traffic.
So what happens is upload goes up,
with this traffic, you upload a lot.
And so the traffic becomes symmetric.
Symmetric means the
download and upload become
equal. Normally you
don't upload anything,
You generally download
more, 10 times more than
the upload, or 100 times
more sometimes, and so
that is what the networks
are designed for. And
there are other reasons,
but that is one reason.
So with peer to peer, the
carriers don't like it because now
their networks become the bottleneck.
Their links become the bottleneck.
You become unhappy with them
because you are not able to upload at the
speed that you want to. OK.
Second thing is, it's
difficult to authenticate.
You don't know who you are
talking to. You don't know the program
that you are getting, and don't
get programs by torrent, by the way.
The program you're
getting is authentic. OK, it is
not a virus. It doesn't
have a virus, or whatever
it is, right? So it's very insecure.
Users need incentives, as the
second thing, is why would somebody
want to give you something for free?
So there is a reason for that.
BitTorrent has been designed for that.
[student question]
Yeah, so they do authenticate. I
mean, in that case, it is not unknown here.
Process communication, now
this is a little bit about Linux.
An operating systems
course, actually not
Linux. It is an operating
systems course and
Linux is just one operating system,
Windows is another, and Mac is some
version of Linux. So in most operating
systems, and particularly Linux,
actually, Linux is a son of Unix,
So in the case of Unix.
And Unix was designed
a long time ago by AT&T,
so Unix, they gave the name socket.
They gave the name socket to the
place where you can talk to a process.
So if you have a process
running, and there is
a process here, a process
here, two processes
running on the same
computer. One process
wants to give some data
to the second process.
It will open a socket. OK,
OK, so the same thing
continues in networking. Now,
these two processes are
not on the same computer.
They are on different computers.
Right, and this computer wants to
give something to the
other computer. So then you
open a socket to listen and
open a socket to connect.
OK, so this socket is
the name that Linux uses.
So now this is something
that I assume that all of you already
know from computer science is that
the user part is the user domain
and the operating system part, right?
There you cannot mess up at all. So in
the operating system, we have protocols,
TCP, IP, and so on. And the user
can control these processes up to here.
So basically when they want to send
something, they send it by a socket to the
local TCP-IP module and
the TCP-IP module tells
the remote TCP-IP
module, and by the socket
it comes to the next part.
So I forgot the name. What they
call it on the Windows system.
I think they call them ports. I think. I
mean, I could be wrong on that one,
but the port is coming right next to it. I
don't know. I mean, the answer to what
are they called on Windows? They
might be called sockets too because
The thing is Windows and
Unix came almost at the same time. OK,
so it's not that one borrowed from the
other. They were independently done,
although having said
that, that was early in
the game. Later on,
Unix went like this and
Windows probably followed it.
Yeah, so originally the
socket was for inside one
system. Now we are going
to use multiple systems
and so we're not going to...
The multiple systems we use with
all these ports, turns out we call it a
port, so it is coming up in the next slide
So hold on to that
thought, right? So a port
is where you dock
in, where you connect,
Right, I mean if any ship comes in,
it goes to the port. Right, so
same way, Here, when you -
so that is the word that
has been borrowed for the
computer system. This
is not a computer system,
but we have borrowed that word and
when you connect to some computer we call
it a port at the point when you connect.
So every computer has thousands
of ports. Most of them are closed,
but maybe 510 are open.
OK, so there is a port
number 80 for example.
OK, port number 80 is for HTTP, for that
If on your computer you use a web
server, what the web server will do is open
the Port 80 on your computer. Anybody
can connect to that computer on Port 80.
OK, and you don't have to use Port 80.
You can use port 8080.
You can use port 81. You
can use port 4001. But
people have to know what
port you have opened so
they can connect to that port.
Yeah. Exactly, so the question is
when you write on a web server, the
IP address colon, something that thing.
Something after the colon
is the port number. Yeah.
Does the computer tell
which ports are open?
Huh? Can you speak loudly, please?
What is the point of
having closed ports? So
that is security. You
don't want... I mean I lock
all the ports, at my home they are
closed. OK, because I locked it totally,
nobody can come in.
Right? So security. Yeah.
OK, everybody speak loudly.
I have been hearing
it but still I cannot hear
you so I don't know.
Maybe they're not working.
Yeah, go ahead. OK, so question:
why there are so many ports then?
If only a few of them are being
used? OK, well, I'm in my home,
I have 26 cameras and I need 26
cam ports just for those 26 cameras.
Right now you can count from that,
OK. So you need one port for everything,
you know, for one application.
If a port is closed, can we use it
locally? No. The port is closed means
nobody can use it inside or outside.
Alright? Good questions so far.
So interprocess
communication on the same host.
The operating system
provides the message passing.
And Unix systems called this a
socket, and this is a socket right here
It is a socket.
Right? But now we're having
communication between the computers and so
On the different hosts, we have to go
through the network, and we call it a port
OK, so the port is not here, the
port is right there. It's right there.
OK, so in the network. OK and TCP-IP
connects only to a port from outside.
OK. So now you understand
the port and you know the socket.
So there are a few more things, names,
so you need to go to the IP address.
The IP address is written
down here as shown
before, but generally,
we don't remember
the numbers, we write a name.
And that name gets translated into
the number inside your computer.
OK, so in the network, we only use
a binary address, not even
decimal. But for people,
human beings that is a
decimal. And so we use
a 32-bit address and
we put the port number,
which is the entry point at that address,
and so for example, 21 is FTP and
80 is HTTP. Right?
OK, so why is port 80 for HTTP? So
there is an organization called IETF
Internet Engineering Task Force, which
wrote this protocol and when they write a
protocol they decide what is the standard.
If nobody told you and you are trying to
go to a web server, you
go to port 80, but if they
tell you that no, no,
no, we don't come for 80
I can come for 8080. Then you go to
Port 8080 but they have to tell you that.
Port 80 is the standard
HTTP port. By default.
Each? I'm sorry. What is the question?
Oh OK, you question is that HTTPS
Secure HTTP, does it use the same
port or a different port? That could,
I think it is probably the
same port, but it could be
negotiated. What happens
is, as will come later on,
First you connect with
HTTP and then you negotiate
security. I mean, but
firstly when you connect -
At least in the case of Mail,
I know for sure in the case of
Mail we use 547, 447 etc etc,
which is for secure Mail as compared to
25 for insecure mail.
So we use different ports.
Alright, I think it is different ports
so the answer to your
question is a different port,
because when you come
to that different port we don't
give you any information until we
have gotten your security cleared.
Alright. So we got that.
There are two transport protocols.
TCP and UDP. The main difference
is that TCP is reliable.
Reliable means once
you give it to something
to give it to somebody,
you can know, just like
FedEx, UPS, that it's reliable.
Packet sequence number is required,
and therefore each packet has a number,
1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, and each packet gets
acked, so when it reaches the destination
it gets acknowledged. I
got four, I got five I got 6.
And lost packets are retransmitted.
If you got four and six but didn't get 5,
something happened to
five. We have to resend it.
And therefore it may
cause long delays. Because
you know, if you're sending
it to Germany and now
suddenly you heard that next three
days later that they didn't get box #5.
You have to resend five before TCP will
give the whole thing to the next person.
So the TCP reassembles
the whole packet, right? So
it may cause delays.
Connection-oriented service -
and it is therefore connection
oriented. Now this is a difference.
Some people get confused between
the TCP connection and the connection
we talked about in the telephone
network. In the telephone network,
The path is predetermined. Right, and
that path is followed by every single bit.
In this case, the path is not
determined, but the ends are determined,
and before the first bit goes
around, the TCP will set up a
connection with an end-to-end connection.
So this is only end-to-end connection.
OK, and the path can keep
changing. Something can
break, something can
come, but the connection.
Packets will find the destination
and once they reach the destination,
the destination TCP will
count the packet number
and so on, so forth. Send
the acknowledgment back.
And so it is an end-to-end
connection. Yeah.
Does each packet had the same path?
The answer is no. Each packet could have a
different path, and that's the whole reason
for going to the Internet rather
than the old telephone network.
Alright. Good for reliable and
delay insensitive applications,
so it is good for if you
need that reliability,
so if you are sending
your paycheck,
Better send it by TCP. Right?
Because if 1 digit was missing
in that number instead of 10,000
you got 1000, you will be very unhappy
so you want everything to
be reaching their destinations.
Applications -
Email, HTTP, FTP and remote
These are the applications
that use TCP. UDP,
now if you have this, why
do we need another one?
We have some applications which
cannot wait and so they use UDP.
UDP is unreliable.
So there is no need for a sequence
number, if you want to put it,
you can put it, but it is not required.
You just send the packet, it's delivered,
got it, didn't get it, too bad. OK.
Not acked, no retransmission.
There is no question of waiting
for anything, the packets come
and go. Packages come and go.
Connectionless Service, You don't
need to set up a connection beforehand.
The end-to-end
connection. It is good for
loss tolerant,
delay-sensitive applications.
Can you think of a loss-tolerant,
delay-sensitive application? Anybody?
Video! Zoom, right! So anything
such as TV, video, or even voice.
You might not be getting 10% of
my voice, but you can make it out.
That is loss-tolerant. Our
ears have loss tolerance,
same thing for eyes.
We have loss tolerance
If the package is not
going to make it to the TV,
you know the TV can
make it up for you. Basically,
TV's are designed to
make up the packets for
you because what they
do is they just put the
same previous screen
and all you see is a
1-microsecond delay,
or a 30-millisecond delay,
which you don't even see.
Alright, so most of our senses
are loss tolerant and therefore...
but they are delay sensitive, so you cannot
make them wait for five minutes.
And so Telephony, streaming.
Those are the applications
that use UDP, Skype, Zoom. OK.
Alright. Any question about
TCP/UDP? Yeah, there's a lot.
I mean, a whole TCP/UDP module coming up.
[student question]
How come DNS runs on UDP?
So we will come to that, so just
hold on to that question.
It's covered in this module.
DNS is covered in this module.
Alright, so back to the next module.
Application layer protocols -
HTTP, FTP, SMTP, DNS, P2P, Skype.
And so we'll go through them one by one.
And I put in red here "control plane."
So I have to introduce that
word to you, is that there are some
applications that you have always
used. There are some applications you
have never used, DNS,
for example. You never
knew that there is a
protocol called DNS -
Everybody knows, but
generally, you don't use DNS
directly. DNS is used by the network.
By your computer, for you.
So anything that the user
does is called the user plane.
Anything that this system does to help
the user is called the control plane.
OK, so DNS is something
that is done in the control plane.
It's done underneath your request, you
are saying I want to go to www.google.com.
And the system will translate
that name and put the IP address.
Right, that translation
happens in the control plane.
Actually, in the telephony days, when you
you gave the phone number of
your mom, the telephone company will
figure out where this
phone number is, which city
it is and where it is
right now at this minute.
Right, if it is a cell phone number,
all that is in the control plane.
[student question]
Right, so the security
part is control plane
OK, so just hold on to that. Yes,
it is. But HTTP is coming next.
Alright, so this much
is the architecture, and
this is the summary of
the first part of chapter 2.
First is, you learned that P2P is
more scalable than client-server.
The second thing you learned is that
applications exchange messages using
operating system
sockets and then the
applications communicate
with the hostnames,
addresses and ports. So now you
know what is a name, what is an address
What is a port, what
is a socket, etc etc And
the applications use
transports: TCP and UDP.
TCP is for reliability and
UDP is for delay sensitivity.
OK, five key messages. So HTTP.
HTTP, we will go through the concept.
A sample web page, messages, cookies.
Servers, and conditions
So the concept,
And by the way, this is
the work that was done.
in UIUC, I mean right here in Illinois
And now, I could be wrong on this one.
That the guy in France who
discovered World Wide Web,
He probably just discovered
the basic infrastructure
as to how to do it.
I don't know who wrote the first
client. And I think the first time
was written in Illinois. And that became
successful. And then the guy founded
the company is called
Netscape. But I could be
totally wrong on this.
OK, so this is the protocol
to get the web page.
And so you need a
client which we call a
browser, and you have
so many different browsers
Firefox, previously used in
Mozilla, which was the original one -
And now we have Edge and
Internet Explorer and whatnot, right?
So these are all clients. On
the server side, you need a
Server, which you have never
seen, but you can get it from
Microsoft or Apache and so forth.
So there are many servers, right?
Free and paid. And a web
page is basically a group of
objects, and they are
called objects because
this could be voice, video, or text.
And the objects will be text,
images, and files. URL is the locator,
uniform resource locator.
So for example, if I write down http://
www.cse.wustl.ed/~jain
/cse473-09/sample.htm, That's a URL.
You already knew that. Before,
URL because you just swap in
is called Uniform Resource
Locator It's called uniform because
This is uniform in the whole world, that's
all it is. OK, it's the global standard.
Alright. And now, of course, the clients
could be running any operating system.
There is a Mac,
there is a PC and the
server could be running
any operating system
and any server. This is a
web server from Apache.
OK, so. Now HTTP uses TCP.
And actually. Yeah,
it uses TCP and it has two different...
Actually, it started out stateless.
Stateless means the server does
not remember any previous
history. What it means is that there are
millions of people coming to my
server. And if I remember everybody, what
they're doing, what they're saying.
Then I would have so much memory,
disk, and all that required to
store all that. So this server doesn't
remember what you did,
OK? And so you give the
question to the server, and
the server answers that question.
Now, so for example, you ask the question
what is HTTP? And I
say, that is hyper traffic -
and you say what if I add S? Now, I
don't remember what to add that S to.
This is a new question. It's not complete.
Right, so every question
has to be complete.
That is called
stateless because I
don't remember your previous question.
And therefore the
TCP connections are
non-persistent, which
means that when you send me
the question, before
sending the question, you
wanted to make sure that
your question gets to me.
You set up a TCP
connection. I gave you the
answer. We closed the
connection, we're done.
Non-persistent means now, next question,
next TCP connection, next
answer, done. Connection closed.
And so that was non-persistent,
opens a new TCP connection, gets one
object and close. And that was
very slow. That became very painful.
That was the original HTTP, right? So
then they said OK, we will do persistence.
With persistence, you open one
connection and you can keep
asking a few questions and then you
close the connection, and then you
come back and you ask more questions.
So again we won't remember across
the connections. After the connection,
Maybe I can remember. Right? So the server
leaves the connection open after sending an
object and closes on timeout. And
if you don't ask any more questions
it will close the connection.
Right? So basically if a web page
comes in, and then you didn't
click on any links on that web page,
then I don't know
whether WashU will close
the connection. But if
it was something which was
more of a paid site, like if
you're buying your airline ticket,
they will just say sorry,
you're timed out, done.
WashU doesn't care. They
will close the connection,
You won't know it, but if you click it
again they will open the connection again -
but every question has to be complete.
So the web pages are written in
HTML. HyperText Markup Language.
So if you want to
write a web page, which
many of you have. If
not, we will write today.
It is written in a language, not in
a protocol. HTTP is the protocol.
HTML is the language.
So here is my webpage. This webpage
contains my picture and
my name. If you go to my
web page you will find a lot
more than this, but this is simplest.
OK, to prepare this I
had to write this code.
Alright? So HTML. In HTML, everything
starts with . So this one says
inside this angle
brackets. Then the header.
And the header starts
with the word HEAD and
then ends with the word /HEAD.
OK, this will be a backslash. So
basically HEAD and /HEAD and then BODY
This is the thing that will
be shown here. And it says
that the first thing I want
to show you is the image,
and its source is jain.jpg
We show this guy, an image.
This image, which is in
my computer, and then
they break, , and
put the text "Raj Jain."
OK, and then that's the end of
the body and end of the page.
OK, how many of you have written HTML?
Alright, so this is all unnecessary,
so those of you who have done HTML,
please do. And then, if nothing else,
write a similar program for yourself.
OK, with your own picture and in my...
I don't think I have in this in this class,
but my next class everybody has to write
their own web page, and if you are
anybody, you are going to look for a job.
You have to prepare one web page because
nowadays you don't send resumes by Mail.
You send them on GitHub or whatever
place you can find free space. And put it.
Alright, so this is HTML.
Now, back to the protocol.
Protocol is when you want to get a page,
you send a command, and HTTP is one of the
protocols which are written in
English. In ASCII to be exact.
So it is not like 010101,
if you want to read
HTTP messages,
they are very difficult to
read because there are binary.
OK, only computers can read them.
HTTP was designed so that humans
can read it, and computers can read it.
In fact, it is probably more difficult
for computers than for humans.
Humans probably can easily read
GET. OK, so you send the word GET.
Followed by a space, followed
by a backslash and then tilde,
jain, blah blah blah and then a
space and then HTTP/1.1.
So what we're saying is, please
give me this thing using this protocol.
HTTP has many protocol versions,
and 1.1 version is what I'm speaking,
So don't speak to me in
whatever other versions you have.
OK. And the host on which you
have to look for this is www.cse.edu.
So we have broken the URL into two parts.
This is what is called the Directory.
Or the object, and this is the host.
What you would have typed into Firefox or
you know whatever you are using,
HTTP: blah blah blah and then www.cse
and then you had to put this ~jain
right? Here they are broken into two parts.
The first part is the
host, second part is
the object. And then
I'm saying the connection
closes, meaning after you give it to me,
you can close the connection. I am Mozilla.
OK, and Mozilla 4.0.
And I only speak EN, English.
OK, if you write Fr then you will
get the answer in French, alright.
And so people write all their languages,
whatever language. But I only need EN.
Alright, so these things are
in asking, the sense
that you write this
carriage return, right?
This carriage return,
write this carriage return,
write this carriage
return, carriage return.
2 carriage returns.
Two carriage returns
means I'm done. On my side.
Give me the answer.
Well, how do you negotiate
which HTTP protocol to use?
Users decide what you can speak. There is
no negotiation, the client is the winner.
Right? The server will say sorry, I don't
speak it, and then you may not get it,
but you know, generally servers
are smart. A lot more money is put into
keeping them up to date. Clients may
not be updated for years. Yeah, go ahead.
Sorry?
Why is it not changed to binary?
Oh OK, well nowadays most newer
protocols of HTTP are ASCII because we're
not in short of bits
anymore. See, the original
protocols were written
at 410 bits per second and
every bit was worth its money, and
you will see those protocols where
they try to save every one bit. Here
we have plenty of bits, so we don't care.
So nowadays, debugging is
more important than anything else,
so you can debug this very quickly,
and if you suppose
something is not working,
you can just look at
the ASCII message
using anything and then even go:
this tilde was not there, you know
you know, the message was not sent.
This is very easy to debug and write.
OK so don't go to HTTPS yet.
HTTPS is secure, which
means there's a lot of security,
so I wouldn't cover it
until the end of this course.
The last module is security.
Anything else? Right, so
there are four things here,
The method - The method is GET.
OK, there are other methods in a minute.
We will get them. URL.
So this is the URL object
actually and this is the host, so
This is the object and then the version,
this is the version, and the header fields,
and these are the fields: Host:,
Connection:, User-agent:, Accept-Language:
So these are all the header fields, all
the header fields are followed by a colon.
OK. Alright. Now.
This is the message format. Every
message will start with a method,
a space, followed by URL.
A space followed by
version, cr, lf, Followed
by header field name,
followed by Colon followed
by value of that field. CRLF, CRLF, CRLF,
CRLF and then some text.
OK. Yeah. The CRLF...
carriage return and line feed.
So those are the parts
we do in the DOS days
we do it every second.
CRLF, carriage return and line feed
so the old typewriters had those fields
Old typewriters, old typewriters if
you're typing, there was a key called CR,
carriage return, and if you press
that, the carriage will come to this end
but it will not go down. Right, if
you want to go to the next line.
You put the key LF.
Line feed. So, it will
go to the next line, and if
you don't want to go to
the return, you want to just
go here, right here to the
next line, then you will say LF
and it will go down. That is
how I typed my Ph.D. thesis.
If you want to write X raised to the
one, you write 1 and then you come
down and write X. Alright, it
was not like X underscore or
or whatever. I mean there was no -
The typewriter. Now that's CR LF.
CRLF is an in line character.
Actually, it's just
control M and control L.
Control+M is I think 13 L is Ctrl+ML...LM
yeah, 13 and 10 in ASCII. Now this is this
is beyond this course, but every character
has a number associated with it,
and up to whatever number ASCII goes,
up to 128 or 255 or whatever I want.
So this CR is 13. LF is 10. Yeah.
OK, it doesn't matter.
CRLF is fixed, it is part of
ASCII. I mean this is totally after
running to the operating system. ASCII
messages can go from any computer
type to any computer type from any
operating system to any operating system,
and so they have been
standardized worldwide.
ASCII stands for
American standards.
For something, something.
So that is an American standard
and it became an
international standard,
and now the international
standard is called
something else and I forget the name.
So basically. These are the standards
for character transmission.
Right, and once you write
down, if you use something
else, then you could put that in the
header field that I'm
not using ASCII, I am
using something else,
and then you use that.
Alright, so here is the
message. This is the response.
So the response is HTTP 1.1, 200 OK
Connection: close. date: this
month. Server:, Last modified:,
Content length: 6500, Content
type: text/HTML, and then lots of data.
Now let me read one by one. So
what this server is saying is that
I'm giving you the answer in 1.1, and
200 means OK. So it answered twice.
200 for the computer to read.
OK for the human being to
read. They are the same thing.
Whenever 200 comes, it is always followed by
OK. Because we cannot remember the number.
The computer cannot read OK so easily.
So the computer sees 200 and says OK,
I got it. Alright, and
here are the numbers -
200 OK. 300 moves permanently.
400 bad request. 404 not found.
505 HTTP version not supported. Yeah.
Move permanently, the question
is whether it will
give you, It is optional.
It most likely will because that
is why it will say permanently.
Otherwise, you will get a 404.
So in my system I manage a website,
where those pages you might go through,
I have 70,000 pages. OK, it
is bigger than any company.
I have to do all this, is that
whenever I move a page
from here to there, I
have to put a pointer at the
old place. That I'm
moving it here, so you will
get the message saying that it has been
moved, and it will give you the new one.
If I miss a page then you will get a 404.
How was it?
Oh, this was user agent.
You send this and then you get
that. I'm sorry. What is your question?
Can somebody translate for me?
I mean I'm not getting it, yeah?
What is the user? Oh user agent?
OK, OK, OK, alright. So
here's the thing. Here is the thing
So the question is good.
Why Mozilla and why not Edge?
Somebody might do something special
just for them. OK, for example in Google,
I'm not going to use this, and I'm going to
use some extension they might come up with.
Then the web server
will know who is causing
this trouble, and
how to answer them.
And also they keep track of
users, you can go to any website and
you can figure out how many
people came to you from Windows,
how many people came to you
from this browser, that browser?
Every browser has slight differences.
OK, did that answer your
question? OK, go ahead.
Would they still answer? The messages
that are requested not specified?
Yeah yeah, so the thing is,
most of these header fields are
not required. OK, but you
need to... see this next slide?
You need the method, URL, and version.
And there could be more of these. I just
showed you some. I mean there are tons of
others that are not here. There are more
optional arguments, yeah. So now
this is a response and it
has similar header fields.
Actually, the next slide
showed you the same thing,
version... the response
starts with version, space,
Status code, space, phrase,
CRLF. header field name,
colon, space, value, CRLF, CRLF,
and so on. So going back to this.
It says I'm closing the
connection. This is the time today.
And this is the server. Why is it
servicing the WashU server? You know,
you know that it is not
Microsoft and therefore
you cannot read Microsoft
extensions with me, yeah?
Yeah, this is another system connection.
Yeah, and then the object that I'm
sending you was last modified in 2009.
OK, and its length is
6500 and it is a text.
OK, and then whatever
else is there. Video, yeah.
Byte, yeah.
So most of these are
standardized now. Microsoft
might have put some
things I don't know about,
but most of these are standardized.
So that is where you need the HTTP
RFC. So what you have to do is you can
download the HTTP protocol RFC
from ITF. It tells you all the fields, all
the header fields,
everything, all the rules, and
when people implement it,
they read that RFC. Yeah.
Yeah, that is standardized
by RFC, by by ITF.
Yeah, these codes have been standardized
by ITF. These are standard codes.
Is that the question? Oh, what is
a bad request? Because you put
something that I couldn't understand. I
mean, let's say instead of GET you said GTE
I don't know what GTE is.
It's a bad request, yeah? Yeah.
Yeah, it's up to the
server. It's up to the server.
I mean the thing is, some
servers will take the old
versions, very very old versions, and
some will say no more than five years old.
Except this server.
OK. Alright, so this I
already went through,
so the next is something that you
would do yourself, and you can do it.
By typing on your computer on a DOS box.
Telnet might not work
because nowadays telnet
has a bad reputation,
so it was working at some
time but may not
work now. But basically,
you can set telnet to
www1.cse.wustl.edu 80.
What it says is that I want to
connect to port 80 of this one.
Tell me the protocol that
will connect you to that
port. Now, once you're
connected to that port,
then you can type GET this host.
Carriage return and carriage return
And now you see, this
is a good example of
what people had asked.
What about other fields?
I don't need the
other field. I don't care
for the language, I
don't care for anything.
Connection TCP close, nothing.
So this carriage return carriage
return means that I'm done.
OK. Now if it is a server over there,
it will say HTTP 1.1, 200 OK date.
Server, Accept content, language, and then
it will send you this text, it will
say. Left angle bracket HTML,
right angle bracket and then return
and then  and  and then
and "this is a sample
text"  . But these
characters will come
back to your computer.
Now your browser will change that to this.
What you will see is,
this is a sample text.
Because this is HTML.
That HTML got translated
to this page on your screen.
So now you see the role for HTML and HTTP.
HTTP is required to talk.
HTML is required to present.
Any questions? And
everything comes
character by character,
so the last character
in this angle bracket - Yea, go ahead.
Yeah, and this was right here where it
says Entity Body. Or in the previous one.
It says entity body.
So this 233 you can
calculate right from here.
1, 2, 3, 4, 5, Amazon, so forth.
You will get 233 characters.
Please. Yeah.
OK, the question is content-type,
is this a common example?
Or a random example? This is one of
the most common ones, and let me put
it this way because originally,
the pages used to be just the text.
Nowadays there are
very few pages, just plain
text alone. Right, so
they might have sound
they might have, you know? So what
will happen is I'm going to come to you
Now you might get many
different contents. OK, so
there could be sound or
something like that right?
And the sound is coded with some method.
So MIMO, encoding will come later on.
So this could be different. Yeah, go ahead.
Right, it could be something else.
So there are many different content
types. Again, this is standardized by ITF.
What type it is. Any other questions?
Alright, so there is
your homework. Actually,
one more hands-on
and then the homework,
so listen carefully. So here.
You said get this one.
And then the answer comes
back. And this is the answer.
OK, so you see a list
starts with 404 not found.
OK, but then it also sent this
part, and this server made this up.
So on your screen you will get "not
found" because it was set there, and then
actually it said here, not found.
That's why it's bold, and then it will say
the requested sample was not found
on this server, and it says I'm this guy.
So whatever they want
to say, this server might
say there, right? So you
got the error message.
This one?
This output.
DOCTYPE HTML -
So here's the thing. This
server decided that it wants
to put before HTML, this thing.
And there are lines before HTML.
OK, because nowadays
we don't just speak HTML.
We speak many other markup
languages. XML is more common. Right,
Basically I mean,
this came from the
server, and this is valid...
OK, the server was decided
right here, www1.cse.wustl.edu.
Yeah, then it will not go anywhere.
You will get "host not found."
Now here what happened
was that zero doesn't exist.
The previous one was some other
number that probably existed right?
So this is what it is. Is that
depending upon you know what you
request, what the answer comes
back, the answer comes back in HTML.
And. Then you see it on your screen.
Cookies. We are going
very slow. Alright, so the
problem with HTML was that
we couldn't remember the next or
previous question, right? There
are stateless, so what do we do?
So what they did was they said
OK, Alright, I will remember you. I will
give you a number which, when you ask the
next question please give
me that number, so I will
go back to my disk and
figure out what number -
What you did before. Everybody gets
a number. And that is called a cookie.
OK. And so. You go to.
In your computer,
all these cookies are
remembered from the
last time you talked to eBay.
It gave you the number 8734.
So you go to the message. And.
OK, I think this would be the eBay server,
but we will come back
to that. It should be eBay
Server. So you go back
and send this message.
And it will say OK, I hear your answer.
But next time give me the number 1678.
OK, so this says here is my cookie, 1678
and then it will give you the answer and
then the next one is 1678, still
1678, and the response is done.
OK, so basically it is a contact. This is
how it would remember what you are doing.
You are buying refrigerators.
Write X, it remembers that in its disk,
you don't have to say the whole thing all
over again. You can just give a number.
Go ahead with your question.
OK, this is the eBay server.
Yeah, I think that was a typo.
Hey, can you take, set
up the slides, write it down?
Just give it back to me, we can correct it.
Yeah, you have to get Amazon's cookie.
I mean I think what happened
here is some part of it came from the
book and some part I created.
or this is Amazon's 1678. Yeah,
so the thing is here you want -
OK, so you're right.
Basically, this is Amazon's -
So what this is showing is,
The cookie file is very long,
in some cases it is a
file, in some cases it is just
an entry in a storage
directory. So there is one entry
that says 8734, but we're not
using it. We're talking to Amazon.
So we don't have any cookie.
Right, and then Amazon
gives the cookie 1678.
So now we use that for
Amazon, but 8734 doesn't change.
Yeah.
OK, the question is: do
we have just a number? No.
So cookies started with numbers.
Now they have become so big.
They are very complex. OK,
but the concept is the same.
From each website.
I think it is very confusing if you
have multiple cookies from each host.
I mean you could have WW1 one cookie, WW2
second cookie, but if you had W1 5 cookies,
that would be very confusing.
You have to send the cookie back.
Yeah, right, so they are becoming large for
security reasons, not for anything else.
So the thing is, there is a lot of security
information because here is the thing:
when you go to the bank and it says sorry,
we don't recognize you, it's because you
didn't have a cookie. If you had a cookie,
they will recognize you and then
they will ask for your password.
Well, that's what it does, it's
not the holistic history
you put in the cookie.
You could put it, but then
you know it is too much.
The cookie is used only to give back to
the context, and in general,
it's more for in recognizing
that you have been here before,
that you are not a new computer
trying to reach my bank. OK. Yeah.
What is the breakdown of information
for the server versus the client?
The client returns the cookies
and the server supplies the cookies.
And the cookie has to be
stored on the client side, yeah.
Alright. So.
So everybody understands cookies now,
so I'm not going to talk
about cookies anymore. It's
this totally new concept
called a Proxy Server.
Now it so happens that most of the
people are doing exactly the same thing.
OK, if the news comes
out that somebody is, you
know whatever is
happening in the world today.
Not much is happening today
in the world. Everybody is just
talking about one thing,
right. I'm not going to
talk about that thing. So
the thing is, if everybody
talks about one thing, then why do 1500
people have to go to the server and find
out when we can locally
cache it. What they do is,
WashU, for example, to save its
traffic would put a server here, which is
called a proxy server,
which is not a real server.
When anybody wants to
know about that common thing,
it has the answer already. It will give you
the answer. If we didn't have the answer,
then we'll go to the original server and
get the answer and then remember it.
For example, you want to know what
is the score of whatever our team is.
Right, why do we have to
go to the original server?
We can just know the
score when one person asks,
second person asks, third person
asks, we have the answer. Yeah.
Great. How do you know
that it has not been updated?
Everything comes with
a lifetime and everything
comes with the last
modified. That's a good one.
So here we saw the lifetime somewhere,
last modified was there somewhere, right?
Last modified. So last modified
means that this field that you are getting
was last changed 10 years ago. Right, and
it will give a lifetime with another field,
which says lifetime 10 seconds. So if you
have to answer this again 10 seconds later,
please check again. If you want
the stock market price of IBM stock,
it will have a lifetime of a second.
OK. And if you want
the length of the United
States, all bits of
the United States,
that area of the United
States will have a lifetime
of 200 years. I don't know.
Maybe at least a year.
OK, depending upon the climate change.
Right, you got it? OK. Proxy servers.
Proxy server is your local cache.
So you can get a conditional
GET. Conditional GET is
Basically, you can say to
this server, please give me this
object if modified since.
If it has been modified
in the last three days,
please give it to me.
Otherwise, I have it.
Alright, and you can send
lots of this modified
since request, hundreds
of them, and maybe
two will come back.
Everything else is fine.
Alright, so I get not modified,
not modified 304, and then
if it has been modified you
will get the modified data.
So that brings us to the end of HTTP.
HTTP summary has 6 things
here. We have client server protocol,
First of all, it is not peer-to-peer, there
is a server, there is a client and it uses
ASCII-based messages. Web
pages are generally written in HTML.
The language is HTML, and
it is either a non-persistent
or persistent connection.
And cookies allow
servers to maintain these states.
That's why the cookies were introduced.
Proxy servers improved performance
by caching the frequently used pages.
Conditional GETs allows proxy
servers to reduce the Internet traffic,
so the conditional get was introduced
so that the proxy servers don't
have to get everything every time.
There is homework, 2A: HTTP
So here is the response from the
server, just the response. And...
And here's the answer. Basically,
the response continued up to here,
and these are the 5
questions. Was this
server able to successfully
find the document?
When was the document
last modified? How many
bytes are there? What
are the last five bytes?
And just assume that
the byte ends right here.
I'm sorry, what are you saying?
E-tag, yeah, that could be a cookie.
OK, so anyway, what are the first 5
bytes of the document being
returned? The first 5 bytes are
right here. And it's angle
bracket to angle bracket, OK?
And did this server agree
to a persistent connection?
So that is what you will see. Whether
it was persistent and non-persistent.
I'm not going to give you the answer, but
the answer is right there in front of you.
OK, and there's a lab.
The lab is, you have
to find the IP address.
I think you did this last time, did you?
OK, so now this is slightly
modified. So I think this is a
little bit ahead of time,
but let me just explain
this lab. This needs
explanation. We have time.
So the thing is, how
is the name translated to an address?
The very first thing is that your
computer has a file in which names
and addresses are written
down. It's called the host file.
So if there is a host file and in that
it says www.google.com becomes
this, then that's the answer, that's done.
If it is not found in
the host file, then
there's a name server
to whom we go and ask.
And if that name server
has the answer, will give
it to you. If they don't
have it then they will
ask their own server,
so it could go on
forever, right? But here
we are assuming that
it is on your host file. Alright.
So modify the host file to map
www.google.com to map to Yahoo's IP
address. And then ping to google.com.
Notice that this is
pinging too. And the host
file is located here,
and I don't know for Mac.
I'm sorry I've never had a Mac,
but in Windows, it is at this location.
Windows\System32\drivers\etc\hosts.
And somebody
can just tell me where
the file is for Mac
and I can just put this on this slide.
Do you know where it is on the Mac?
The host file?
OK anyway, just try and find it. Then
we can put it. Yeah, next question, yeah.
Yeah, so finding the
address is a very easy thing.
You already did that lab before, right?
Well, I mean here is the thing. OK.
So you got the point taken off? No, no
no, it's OK. I wouldn't take out the point.
I mean, The thing is,
if you got IPV6, I've got
IPV6. I mean, this is not
wrong. Yeah, go ahead.
What was the question?
Yeah, any IP version is fine.
Alright, so the thing is,
So you find google.com
and you find yahoo.com, both
addresses you have to
find, and then put in the
host file that google.com translates
to this address and see if it will do that.
Now here is the thing.
There's a slight problem with
this lab, and it might be
the case that nowadays
the browsers have become very,
very clever and they will see that this
something is wrong with
this guy's computer. It is
not google.com and it
will just crash it right there.
It will say no no no. Sorry, you are wrong.
But in the previous cases, we just used
to go wherever you
wanted to go, so let's see
how it handles. But
then you find the domain
name and country. So that's another
thing is that you have to find the domain
name of this. Given any address, you should
be able to find where it is. China, Russia,
India, wherever right?
This is the website, you go
there, put the address,
it tells you where it is.
Find the owner who
owns the website. You can
go to this place and
you can find the owner of
anything, who owns rajjain.com.
We still have 10 minutes,
so please don't go anywhere. And
the name server of the wustl domain,
what is the name
server of wustl.edu? So if
you go to this place
and you ask for the name,
the server will tell you
who the name server
is, and where is the
name server is located.
So all of this information is public
information. If somebody ever hits you with
anything then you can
figure out where in the
world they are. And
then and so on, so forth.
It's very easy because all
you do is plug it into a website.
Alright, continue. OK,
now electronic mail. I
still have 10 minutes. I
gotta use every minute.
So. Electronic mail, uses a protocol called
SMTP, simple mail transfer protocol.
OK, and it is also client server, so,
The servers are speaking with SMTP.
And the agents
are also. Basically,
The protocol is SMTP, so
from one server to the next.
Several are using SMTP
and the user agents also
speak SMTP. So, the
outgoing message queue.
So when you send a message,
it goes into the server and it
stays there in a queue.
Mail is not instantaneous.
Messages send whenever they can send.
Right, so it stays in the queue and from
there it could go to some other queue.
It stays there, then from there it
goes to some other queue.
So basically the mail
servers have to figure
out where to go next,
but it goes through
many servers and in the end
finally waits at the final user server.
So if it is going to this
user it will wait here.
If it is for this user
it will wait there, and
then the user will pull it out and so on.
So it is a simple mail transfer protocol.
This is also a very
old protocol, and
therefore it uses only
7 bit ASCII messages.
There's another complication.
ASCII is only 7 bit. 7 bit means 2^7,
127 is the maximum. Zero
to 127. Right, and so all binary
objects have to be converted. Now,
this was done in 19-, maybe 70s, right.
So the thing is at that time we didn't know
about sound and video and things like that.
Now if you're going to send
sound, what do we do?
We convert that into ASCII.
We take your bits, sound bits,
convert that into ASCII, and then at
the other end, convert it back
into sound. Alright? 7 bit ASCII.
All binary objects have to
be converted to ASCII and use
port 25 at the server. So
this is a standard port 25.
Now, here is a message.
So you talk again in ASCII.
You can set telnet to this host
using Port 25 because 25 is
spoken by the mail server. If you do this
and if it worked on your computer nowadays,
much of this doesn't work anymore
because telnet is very insecure, so
most people might have banned
telnet. But assuming that it is working,
then you can talk to port 25
and then as soon as you connect,
the server will say 220 post office.
Blah blah blah. 75, ready, at this time.
Right, so it says that I am
this guy, you connected to me. Then you
say hello. And because I don't know why,
but hello is spelled as HELO.
OK. You say hello, I am
from acm.org and the
server says OK, So I am
supposed to talk to it, and
now this hello is full HELLO
and this is the difference
between these two hello's, is this is
Just a common courtesy
thing, and this is a command.
OK, this is like in the previous example,
in the HTTP we had a GET which was a
command, and everything
else was text after the
colon. So this is after
the colon, whatever it is.
So this is 250, and this
is hello. And then you
say MAIL FROM. So now
you say I want to send a mail
which will be from jain@acm.org.
So we said OK, Sender is OK.
Then you say it is going to
jain@wustl.edu, and the server says,
that's fine. Then you send data,
"this is a test email," blah blah blah
and then you end it
with a dot. Period. Right
there on your computer.
You put a period.
OK, and nothing else on that
line because a period
could be here too
somewhere, right? This
period? That period doesn't
count. When there is a
carriage return, an empty
line, and a period that is
the end of the message.
Now the server will say, I
will queue this mail for delivery.
Fine, the client says
"quit" and the server says
I'm closing the connection.
And done, that's how mail goes.
Of course, you don't
do any of this every day,
because your Outlook
does it for you. Yeah.
How many characters?
OK, so I don't know of any
limitation. The question is
what is the maximum size
mail can be? I mean,
WashU has put a
20-megabyte maximum,
but that is not the mail
limitation, that is WashU putting that
because they don't want to send too much.
Theoretically, yes, yeah.
Yes, the answer is yes, but we
will not talk about authentication
and security until the last
module. So there is a secure email.
Next, was there anything
else? There is an authentication,
but not here. Not in this chapter.
Alright, so HTTP is non-persistent.
TCP-SMTP is persistent.
It is mostly pull, so you are
mostly getting it from the server.
SMTP is mostly push, giving it to
the server. It accepts binary objects,
it accepts only 7 bit
ASCII, one object per
response. You can have
multiple objects per message,
so basically we will talk
about as to how to do multiple objects.
Actually we will not, but there is a way.
There is a way that might be in the book.
There is a way to send multiple objects
one after another. OK, and nowadays
messages do consist of multiple
objects, so let me come back to here.
So basically this is the
difference between the
two. And so then, how
do you get the message?
How do you get the mail? So you can use
SMTP, if it is always accessible. Right?
But most of us are not always accessible,
so we have to use POP and IMAP.
POP is the Post office protocol.
Nowadays we have
version three so it is
called POP3, and Internet
Mail access protocol
is even a newer one, IMAP. And then
you can also use HTTP. So many of
you are using Office 365 or
something where your Mail comes from
Yahoo or Google on the web page. So they're
not using any of this, they're using HTTP.
We are generally using
either POP or IMAP, right?
So we'll talk about that next time.
There's a lab and there is
homework. Both are due next Monday.